Look, I hope you're excited.
기대해도 좋아요
You really should be.
그러는 게 좋을 거예요
You've been through 80% of the course and it's all been building up to this moment.
코스의 80%를 통과했고 그 모든 게 이 순간을 위해 쌓여온 거죠
Today you will be training your own proprietary LLM for for fun and for profit.
오늘 여러분은 자체 개발한 LLM을 훈련할 겁니다 재미와 이윤을 위해서요
It all starts here.
여기서 모든 게 시작돼요
So what is actually involved in today?
오늘날에는 어떤 일이 일어나나요?
We're going to start with some stuff that maybe isn't so thrilling.
별로 스릴이 없을지도 모르는 것부터 시작할게요
We're going to talk hyperparameters one more time.
hyperperameter에 대해 한 번 더 얘기할게요
I've got some essential hyperparameters to go through with you.
여러분과 함께 할 필수 하이퍼파라미터예요
And the reason this is so important is that you're going to be doing some hyperparameter optimization
이게 중요한 이유는 hyperpaameter 최적화를 직접 하실 것이기
yourself.
때문이죠
The fancy word for for trial and error.
시행착오를 뜻하는 고급 단어죠
And you need to understand the context of what it is that you're playing with.
우리가 갖고 노는 것의 맥락을 이해해야 해요
And this is really the opportunity to build something that can beat other models.
다른 모델을 이길 수 있는 걸 만들 기회예요
It's about understanding what kind of levers you've got to experiment with.
어떤 레버를 실험해야 하는지 이해하는 게 중요해요
That is at the heart of the R&amp;D behind building leading models.
건축의 주요 모델에 대한 연구개발의 핵심이죠
So we've got some hyperparameters to talk about.
hyperperameter에 대해 얘기해 보죠
And then we're going to set up a supervised fine tuning trainer, an SFT.
감독하에 소량 조율 트레이너를 설치할 거예요
Trainer, which is the sort of core object behind running this training.
트레이너는 이 훈련의 핵심 객체예요
Um, looking at parts of the TRL library from Hugging Face and then we will kick off.
TRL 라이브러리에서 얼굴 안기 부분을 살펴보고 시작할게요
Our own proprietary LM training process.
우리만의 LM 훈련 과정이죠
It's going to be great.
멋질 거예요
So first of all, though, before we get to the great stuff, we do need to talk about some of the essential
먼저, 훌륭한 내용을 다루기 전에 이 프로세스를 제어하는 필수 hyperperameter에
hyperparameters that control this process, starting with Q Laura, and most of this is stuff that you're
대해 얘기하겠습니다 Q 로라부터요 대부분은 이제 아주 익숙해졌죠
So the first hyperparameter I'll mention is one more time to bring up the target modules.
첫 번째 hyperpaameter는 대상 모듈을 다시 한 번 언급하는 거예요
And I think you now remember exactly what this is.
이제 이게 뭔지 정확히 기억하실 거예요
If you have an architecture of a transformer, a base model like Lama 3.1, it's way too big to try
변압기 아키텍처가 있다면요 라마 3 같은 기본 모델요 첫째, 이 거대한 건축물을 정교하게 다듬기에는
and fine tune this enormous, great architecture.
너무 커요
So instead we pick a few layers in the architecture and we call those layers.
아키텍처에서 레이어 몇 개를 골라 그걸 레이어라고 부르죠
The target modules are the ones we're going to target.
목표 모듈이 우리가 목표로 삼을 것들이죠
We freeze everything.
전부 얼려요
We're not going to try and optimize these weights.
무게를 최적화하지 않을 거예요
There's too many of them.
너무 많아요
Even in these target modules.
이 표적 모듈에서도 말이죠
We're not going to train these.
훈련 안 시킬 거예요
Rather, we're going to have onto one side a lower dimensional matrix that we will train this lower
그보다는 한쪽에 차원 매트릭스를 두고 이 차원 매트릭스를
dimensional matrix and we will apply it to this original target module.
훈련할 겁니다 그걸 이 원래 목표 모듈에 적용하고요
We'll apply it in fact by multiplying them together, using that as a, as a as a delta on the weights
이걸 곱해서 적용할 거예요 여기 무게추를 삼각주로 사용해서요
Um, and so we train these little guys and we apply them to the target modules, selected layers in
이 작은 녀석들을 훈련해서 대상 모듈에 적용합니다 더 큰 아키텍처에서
the bigger architecture that's target modules.
선택한 층이 대상 모듈이죠
And then ah, uh, with this greater 3D goggles as the, as the logo, as the icon.
그리고 더 큰 3D 고글을 로고로 해서 아이콘으로 삼았어요
Uh, R is how many dimensions do we have in this lower dimensional, uh, adapter matrix?
R은 이 저차원 어댑터 매트릭스에 차원이 몇 개 있느냐는 거예요
Uh, it's often common with learning with language learning tasks to start with eight.
언어 학습을 할 때 8단계로 시작하는 경우가 많아요
Um, for this project you're going to see I've got 32 as the R, because we've got so much training
이 프로젝트에서 32가 R인 걸 보실 수 있습니다 훈련 데이터가 아주 많거든요
data that I figured we could use quite a few parameters to learn on.
몇 가지 매개 변수를 이용해 배울 수 있을 것 같았죠
But if that's running out of memory for you, you can you can have eight.
하지만 메모리가 부족하다면 8개를 가질 수 있어요
I actually I should say that the difference between 8 and 16 and 32 was quite marginal.
솔직히 8과 16과 32의 차이는 거의 없다고 봐야겠죠
It did improve things, but not by a huge amount.
상황이 좋아지긴 했지만 큰 차이는 없었어요
So if you have any memory problems, then stick with an R of eight.
메모리에 문제가 있다면 R에서 8을 유지하세요
If you're on a smaller box that will be just fine.
작은 상자라도 괜찮을 거예요
32 is splashing out a bit, but but but it was worth it given the amount of training data we have.
32는 좀 비싸지만 훈련 데이터를 생각하면 비트를 쓸 만해요
Alpha, you may remember, is the scaling factor.
알파는 배율 요인이죠
It's used to multiply up the importance of this adapter when it's applied to the target module.
대상 모듈에 적용될 때 이 어댑터의 중요성을 곱하기 위해 사용되죠
In fact, you may remember there are actually two Laura matrices.
기억하실지 모르겠지만 로라 행렬은 두 개가 있어요
One is called Laura A and one is called Laura B, and the formula is that the change in weights is actually,
하나는 로라 A 하나는 로라 B라고 해요 무게의 변화가 알파형으로 바뀌는
uh alpha.
거죠
The scaling factor times A times B, as simple as that.
배율 인수 곱하기 A 곱하기 B, 간단하죠
That is that's the most maths that we're going to get in this course.
이 코스에서 배울 수 있는 가장 많은 수학이죠. Get it.
And I think that's not not taking it too far.
그 정도면 과하지 않은 것 같아요
So that's as simple as what alpha is.
알파가 무엇인지만큼 간단하죠
It's the scaling factor.
스케일링 요인이죠
And the rule of thumb is to have alpha to be double R.
경험상 알파는 더블 R로 해야 해요
That's what everyone does.
다들 그렇게 해요
By all means you can experiment with other values of alpha.
알파의 다른 가치를 실험할 수 있어요
But but the norm is is to do alpha is two r.
하지만 알파는 R이 두 개인 게 일반적이죠
So we're going to start with an R of 32 and an alpha of 64.
R은 32로 알파는 64로 시작하죠
Quantisation of course is just what we call it when we reduce the precision of the weights in the base
퀀티세이션은 베이스 모델의 무게 중심을 줄이는 것을 일컫는 말이죠
The base model has 32 bit numbers.
기본 모델은 32 비트 번호예요
In it.
네
We reduce it down to eight bits or even down to four bits, which sounds insane.
8분의 1에서 4분의 1까지 줄여요 미친 소리 같겠지만요
We did that with our base model and we saw that we were still getting results.
베이스 모델로 그렇게 했는데도 여전히 결과가 나오는 걸 봤죠
They weren't great results, but I think that would be true for the base model overall.
좋은 결과는 아니었지만 전반적인 베이스 모델은 그렇다고 생각해요
And we did see actually that the eight bit model did better than the four bit model, but they were
8비트 모델이 4비트 모델보다 잘 달리는 걸 확인했지만
both pretty miserable at it.
둘 다 아주 처참했어요
And by all means you can try training with the eight bit model too.
8비트 모델로 연습해 볼 수도 있어요
But we're going to train with a four bit model because that's what will fit in in our in our memory.
하지만 4비트 모델로 훈련할 거예요 우리 메모리에 맞으니까요
And that's, uh, but I'd be interested if you try the eight bit to see whether you get significantly
Get 8 비트를 시도해보고 결과가 확연히 달라지는지
different results.
보고 싶어요
And then the final hyperparameter is a new one that we've not talked about before, except to show you
마지막 hyperpaameter는 새로운 건데 코드 드롭아웃에서 보여드린
it in the code dropout.
것 외엔 얘기한 적 없죠
So dropout is a type.
중퇴도 유형이군요
It's a technique that's known as a regularization technique, of which there are a few, um, which
정규화 기술이라고 알려진 기술인데 몇 가지가 있어요
means that it's a technique designed to prevent the model from doing what's known as overfitting.
과잉 착용이라는 행동을 막기 위해 고안된 기술이죠
And overfitting is when a model gets so much training data, it goes through so much training that it
과잉 충족이란 모델이 훈련 데이터를 많이 받고 훈련을 많이 거쳐서 훈련
starts to just expect exactly the structure of the data in the training data set, and then give back
데이터 집합에 있는 데이터의 구조를 정확히 기대하게 되고 정확히 그 답을
exactly that answer.
주는 거예요
And it starts to to no longer understand the general trends of what's being suggested, but instead
제안되는 것의 일반적인 추세를 더는 이해하지 못해요 대신
it sort of hones in on precisely those words and the prediction that comes later.
그 단어와 나중에 나올 예측에 집중하죠
And as a result of that, if you give it some new point that it hasn't seen in its training data set,
그 결과 훈련 데이터 세트에서 보지 못한 새로운 점을 주면 성능이 아주 떨어집니다
it performs really badly because it's not being learning the general themes, it's being learning to.
일반적인 주제를 배우는 게 아니라 그걸 배우는 거니까요
It's been too much learning the very specifics of this training data set.
이 훈련 데이터 집합의 세부 사항을 너무 많이 배웠어요
I'm being a bit hand-wavy again, but hopefully you get the idea.
또 손으로 비트를 휘젓고 있는데 이해하시길 바라요 get it get it
That's called overfitting when you are too precisely adhering to the training data set and the outcome.
훈련 데이터와 결과에 너무 충실하면 과잉 대응이라고 하죠
And it's not learning the general flavor of what's of what it's trying to predict.
예측하려는 것의 일반적인 맛을 배우는 게 아니에요
Um, and it's that flavor.
바로 그 맛이에요
It's that nuance of what's going on.
뉘앙스가 중요한 거죠
That's what you're trying to teach the model.
모델에게 그걸 가르쳐야 해요
Um, so that's that's the sort of that's the preamble, the explanation of what?
방금 그건 서문인데 뭘 설명하는 거죠?
Of what overfitting is.
과잉이 뭔지에 대해서요
But now, to tell you exactly what dropout does, and it's really simple, what dropout actually does,
드롭아웃의 기능을 간단히 설명하자면 드롭아웃의
uh, is it quite simply removes a random subset of the neurons from the deep neural network.
역할은 심층 신경망에서 무작위로 뉴런을 제거하는 거예요
From the transformer, it takes a random percentage.
변압기에서 무작위로 퍼센트를 얻어요
We're going to start with 10%, takes 10% of the neurons, and it just wipes them out, sets the activations
10%부터 시작할 거예요 10%의 뉴런을 제거하고 활성화 비율을 0으로 설정해서
to zero so that they are not involved in the forward pass or the backward pass.
앞이나 뒤의 패스에는 관여하지 않게 하는 거죠
They're not involved in predicting the next token and they're not involved in optimizing.
다음 토큰을 예측하는 것과 관련 없고 최적화하는 것과도 관련 없죠
It's as if they're just not there.
마치 존재하지 않는 것 같아요
And as a result, every time that you're going through training, the model is seeing a different subset,
그 결과 훈련을 받을 때마다 모델은 90%의 다른 신경망을
a different 90% of the neural network, 10% of them have been removed randomly each time.
무작위로 제거하는 다른 하위 집합을 보게 되죠
And so the, the, the weights are sort of discouraged from being too precise and to and looking too
그래서 추를 조작할 때 너무 정확하거나 너무 정확한 입력 토큰을 사용하지 않게
precisely for one set of input tokens, but instead, because different neurons participate every time
됐죠 하지만 훈련 과정에서 다양한 뉴런이 참여하면서 더
in the training process, it starts to learn more.
많은 걸 배우기 시작했어요
The general theme than learning very specifically how to expect different tokens.
일반적인 주제는 구체적으로 다른 패를 기대하는 법을 배우는 거죠
So it prevents any one neuron from becoming too specialized.
하나의 뉴런이 너무 각화되지 않도록요
It supports this concept of more general understanding in the neural network, in this very simplistic
신경망에 대한 일반적 이해를 뒷받침하는 개념이죠 매번 다른
way of just removing 10% of the neurons from the process, a different 10% each time.
10%의 뉴런을 제거하는 아주 단순한 방법이에요
So that's dropout.
드롭아웃이에요
It's really very simple.
아주 간단해요
When you realize it, it's literally dropping out a bunch of the neurons and the the norm.
그걸 깨달았을 땐 말 그대로 뉴런과 정상 기관이 떨어져 나가고 있었죠
It's usually somewhere in the in the range of 5% through to 20%.
보통 5%에서 20% 정도 돼요
Um, I've picked 10% as the dropout that we're using.
10%는 포기한 사람으로 정했어요
You should absolutely experiment with 5% and 20% and see whether you get better results or not.
5%, 20%로 실험을 해봐야 해요. 더 나은 결과가 나올지 봐야죠. Get it.
It is very much a hyperparameter to be experimented with.
하이퍼파라미터로 실험해 볼 만하죠
Okay, so those are the five hyperparameters for Q.
Q의 하이퍼파라미터 5개고요
Laura, next time we'll talk about five hyperparameters for the overall training process.
로라, 다음에는 전반적인 훈련 프로세스를 위한 hyperperameter 5개를 다룰 거예요